<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <atom:link href="https://marcolucidi01.github.io/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
        <title>Marco Lucidi</title>
        <link>https://marcolucidi01.github.io</link>
        <description>twenty five years old. italian. computer science enthusiast. programmer.</description>
        <language>en</language>
        <pubDate>Sun, 27 Jun 2021 11:18:13 +0000</pubDate>
        <lastBuildDate>Sun, 27 Jun 2021 11:18:13 +0000</lastBuildDate>
        <generator>https://marcolucidi01.github.io/generate</generator>
        <docs>https://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs>

        <item>
            <title>smartctl short self test very slow on a new drive</title>
            <pubDate>Sun, 20 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <link>https://marcolucidi01.github.io/posts/smartctl-short-self-test-very-slow-on-a-new-drive.html</link>
            <guid>https://marcolucidi01.github.io/posts/smartctl-short-self-test-very-slow-on-a-new-drive.html</guid>
            <source url="https://marcolucidi01.github.io/rss.xml">Marco Lucidi</source>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>I recently bought a new 4TB hard drive for my (homemade) nas and started setting
it up. I created a partition table with a single partition and an <code>ext4</code>
filesystem. I then <code>mount</code>ed the partition, but before starting <code>rsync</code>ing my
data, I wanted to do a little <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/S.M.A.R.T.#Self-tests">S.M.A.R.T. testing</a>. the drive only supports
<em>short</em> and <em>long</em> self tests, no <em>conveyance</em>. I went for the short one since
I'm not very paranoid and I already have <code>smartd</code> setup to run tests weekly on
all the nas's disks.</p>
<p><code>smartctl</code> was so kind to tell me that the test will be completed in 2 minutes:</p>
<pre><code>Testing has begun.
Please wait 2 minutes for test to complete.
Test will complete after Fri Jun 18 18:34:03 2021 CEST
Use smartctl -X to abort test.
</code></pre>
<p>I listened to a song while waiting. 5 minutes goes by, song is over, let me
check:</p>
<pre><code>Self-test execution status:      ( 241) Self-test routine in progress...
                                        10% of test remaining.
</code></pre>
<p>ok, 10% remaining, we are almost there. let's wait. and 10 minutes goes by,
still 10% remaining. 20 minutes, still 10% remaining. 25 minutes, still 10%. it
seems to be stuck! it should have completed in 2 minutes, but half an hour has
passed and it still hasn't finished.</p>
<p>I was ninety percent sure that I ran the short test, not the long one. I aborted
the test with <code>smartctl -X</code> and this ugly line got into the self test log:</p>
<pre><code>Num  Test_Description    Status                  Remaining  LifeTime(hours)  LBA_of_first_error
...
# 9  Short offline       Aborted by host               10%         0         -
</code></pre>
<p>which confirmed that it was indeed a <em>short</em> test.</p>
<p>why was it taking so long? faulty disk?</p>
<p>I ran the short test again hoping this time it would finish in a reasonable
amount of time. same story, stuck at 10% remaining after more than 20 minutes. I
then decided to use one of the old tricks that <em>always</em> works with technology: I
rebooted the machine... boom, another nasty line in the log:</p>
<pre><code># 8  Short offline       Interrupted (host reset)      10%         1         -
</code></pre>
<p>I started the test again. meanwhile my <em>google-fu</em> wasn't helping much, everyone
talked about <strong>long</strong> tests being slow, 30+ hours on old disks that were about
to fail. my disk is new, all the smart attributes are perfect. then I read
somewhere that if the disk is doing a lot of I/O i.e.  is being used, the tests
may take longer. ok, makes sense, but there is no data on my disk and no service
is using it yet.</p>
<p>I felt a bit discouraged, maybe I had to return this drive and wait for another
one to arrive etc...</p>
<p>as a last resort, I tried to <code>umount</code> the partition thinking that somehow it
could help. <strong>10 seconds later the test completed without errors</strong>:</p>
<pre><code># 7  Short offline       Completed without error       00%         2         -
</code></pre>
<p>woow! coincidence? at least the disk seems to be good. I immediately started
another short test and completed without errors in 2 minutes!</p>
<pre><code># 6  Short offline       Completed without error       00%         2         -
</code></pre>
<p>ok, tests takes long <strong>only</strong> when it's mounted. strange because <em>nobody</em> is
using the disk (or at least that's what I believed). I thought: &quot;maybe I did
something wrong when I partitioned the disk&quot; and I repartitioned it again,
<code>mount</code>ed again aaand test stuck at 10% remaining.</p>
<p>I didn't know what to do, I wasn't quite sure that the disk was OK and that it
was <em>safe</em> to put data on it. I fired up <code>top</code>** and stared at it for a while
thinking, like when you open the hood of a car trying to figure out what's
wrong. now with cars, that never helped me because I know nothing about cars,
but with computers sometimes it does help. I noticed this process that kept
popping up: <code>ext4lazyinit</code>. mmmm never heard of it, but the name was suspicious.
I found <a href="https://www.thomas-krenn.com/en/wiki/Ext4_Filesystem#Lazy_Initialization">this beautiful page</a> which talks about lazy initialization in <code>ext4</code>
filesystems (emphasis mine):</p>
<blockquote>
<p>When creating an Ext4 file system, the existing regions of the inode tables
must be cleaned (overwritten with nulls, or &quot;zeroed&quot;). The &quot;lazyinit&quot; feature
should significantly accelerate the creation of a file system, because it does
not immediately initialize all inode tables, initializing them gradually
instead during the initial mounting process in background
...
<strong>The &quot;ext4lazyinit&quot; kernel process writes at up to 16,000kB/s to the device
and thereby uses a great deal of the hard disk’s bandwidth</strong></p>
</blockquote>
<p>aaaha so maybe this is the process that is keeping my disk busy and it's slowing
down short self tests! to prove this theory I recreated the filesystem <em>again</em>
using these extended options:</p>
<pre><code># mkfs.ext4 -E lazy_itable_init=0,lazy_journal_init=0 /dev/sda1
</code></pre>
<blockquote>
<p>By specifying these options, the inodes and the journal will be initialized
immediately during creation.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>filesystem creation took quite a while this time, but in the end, no more
<code>ext4lazyinit</code> process and short smart self test completed in about 2 minutes
even with the partition mounted:</p>
<pre><code># 3  Short offline       Completed without error       00%         3         -
# 4  Short offline       Completed without error       00%         3         -
# 5  Short offline       Completed without error       00%         3         -
</code></pre>
<p>another solution was probably to <em>just wait</em> and eventually short tests would
complete rather fast once the disk was no more busy. at least, my &quot;impatience&quot;
let me figure out what was really happening and learn new things which is always
good!</p>
<hr />
<p><small>** only later I discovered <code>iotop</code> which would have helped a lot.</small></p>]]></description>
        </item>

        <item>
            <title>a tetris clone</title>
            <pubDate>Thu, 27 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <link>https://marcolucidi01.github.io/posts/a-tetris-clone.html</link>
            <guid>https://marcolucidi01.github.io/posts/a-tetris-clone.html</guid>
            <source url="https://marcolucidi01.github.io/rss.xml">Marco Lucidi</source>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>this is my first &quot;&quot;&quot;big&quot;&quot;&quot; project in C, made after reading the bible <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_C_Programming_Language">K&amp;R
Second Edition</a> and after taking the Harvard course <a href="https://cs50.harvard.edu/">CS50</a>.</p>
<p>actually I consider this as my &quot;final project&quot; for CS50: I enjoy C so much that
I had to choose it as the main tool for the project.</p>
<p>here a <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=HRttr5_LnvI">demo video</a> and here the <a href="https://github.com/MarcoLucidi01/tetris_clone"><strong>source code</strong></a>.</p>
<h2>why tetris?</h2>
<p>well, first because I like it: I used to play <strong>A LOT</strong> when I was a kid on a
&quot;chinese fake GameBoy&quot; I had and more recently on my smartphone. and then
because I wanted to do something simple within my reach, but at the same time a
bit challenging, considering the language I chose.</p>
<p>also it is often considered as an &quot;Hello, World!&quot; to game development so once in
my life I had to do it.</p>
<h2>the game</h2>
<p>I tried to stick with the classic <em>Tetris</em>, so no &quot;wall kick&quot;, no &quot;hold piece&quot;,
no &quot;ghost piece&quot;, but I applied some &quot;new&quot; features that I like: &quot;soft drop&quot;
(without adding points) and this <a href="http://tetris.wikia.com/wiki/Random_Generator">random generator</a> so that I don't have to
swear to get an <em>I</em>.</p>
<p>keys to control what's on the screen are straightforward:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>LEFT / DOWN / UP / RIGHT</strong> performs classical movements;</li>
<li><strong>H / J / K / L</strong> also performs classical movements. did you recognize them?
they are those of <a href="http://www.vim.org/">vim</a>! I'm a vim addicted and I thought it would be
nice if I could use vim keys to play Tetris =).</li>
<li><strong>SPACE</strong> performs &quot;hard drop&quot;.</li>
<li><strong>P</strong> pause or unpause the game.</li>
<li><strong>E</strong> ends the game when it is paused.</li>
<li><strong>N</strong> starts a new game when the previous is over.</li>
<li><strong>Q</strong> close the program when the game is over.</li>
</ul>
<p>after the end of each game, it saves the level, score and lines along with the
current date and the time spent playing (including pause time) in a text file
called &quot;scores.txt&quot; within the folder in which the executable resides.</p>
<p>for now, there isn't a way to add a nickname (because you know, probably I will
be the only player...).</p>
<h2>the program</h2>
<p>if you haven't notice yet, I used the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ncurses">ncurses</a> library.</p>
<p>two &quot;design choices&quot; I made (I know I probably screw up somewhere) were: write
&quot;reusable&quot; code (in part) and split different things in different files.</p>
<p>here the files tree and a bit of explanation:</p>
<pre><code>project/
        Makefile
        include/
                actions.h
                colors.h
                controller.h
                drawer.h
                game.h
                grid.h
                helpers.h
                tetramino.h
        src/
                controller.c
                drawer.c
                game.c
                grid.c
                helpers.c
                main.c
                tetramino.c
</code></pre>
<p>for the first time in my three months adventure with C, I felt the need to use a
<a href="https://github.com/MarcoLucidi01/tetris_clone/blob/master/Makefile"><code>Makefile</code></a> and it turned out to be veeery useful of course.</p>
<p>in <a href="https://github.com/MarcoLucidi01/tetris_clone/blob/master/src/helpers.c"><code>helpers.c</code></a> there are some helpers functions (youdontsay.jpg). there is
for example a &quot;<code>malloc</code> wrapper&quot; who calls <code>exit(EXIT_FAILURE)</code> if it was not
possible allocate memory. I call it (the wrapper) every time I need memory.</p>
<p><a href="https://github.com/MarcoLucidi01/tetris_clone/blob/master/src/grid.c"><code>grid.c</code></a> contains functions to handle guess what? right, the game grid on
which put blocks.</p>
<p><a href="https://github.com/MarcoLucidi01/tetris_clone/blob/master/include/actions.h"><code>actions.h</code></a> contains an enum of &quot;actions&quot; i.e. commands that modify the
current state of the game. I think their names are self-explanatory.</p>
<p>the &quot;magic&quot; happens in the files <a href="https://github.com/MarcoLucidi01/tetris_clone/blob/master/src/main.c"><code>main.c</code></a> and <a href="https://github.com/MarcoLucidi01/tetris_clone/blob/master/src/game.c"><code>game.c</code></a>: they handle
the game flow.</p>
<p><a href="https://github.com/MarcoLucidi01/tetris_clone/blob/master/src/tetramino.c"><code>tetramino.c</code></a> defines all you need to create a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tetromino"><code>tetramino</code></a>, rotate
or change its shape and blindly put / remove it on / from a grid if it is not
locked.</p>
<p>with <a href="https://github.com/MarcoLucidi01/tetris_clone/blob/master/src/controller.c"><code>controller.c</code></a> instead, you can perform &quot;actions&quot; on a tetramino only
if that action is allowed, depending on the current state of the grid.</p>
<p>that is, to move, rotate or drop a piece, <code>game.c</code> relies on the functions in
<code>controller.c</code> who relies on the &quot;raw&quot; functions in <code>tetramino.c</code> after some
tests.</p>
<p><a href="https://github.com/MarcoLucidi01/tetris_clone/blob/master/src/drawer.c"><code>drawer.c</code></a> takes care of the &quot;ncurses part&quot; drawing the grid, the edges
and some informations. it has a function, <code>refresh_scene()</code>, which is called in
<code>game.c</code> to update what is on the screen when it's time to do so.</p>
<p><code>grid.c</code> and even <code>drawer.c</code> could be easily reused in other projects, e.g. in a
snake clone, tic-tac-toe, ..., basically anything who requires a simple grid,
because I made them &quot;not Tetris specific&quot;.</p>
<p>I tried to keep things as simple as possible (I always try to do this). for
example, I hard coded all possible rotations for each piece in <code>tetramino.c</code>
since in total they are only <em>4 x 7 = 28</em>. in this way I don't have to call a
function to rotate a matrix and sometimes rotate it backwards, but my functions
simply increment or decrement an index in range <em>[0,3]</em>. of course I did this
because the amount of memory used is very low.</p>
<h2>conclusion</h2>
<p>at the end of the day, the main goals of this project were:</p>
<ul>
<li>learn something new;</li>
<li>get a &quot;working&quot; Tetris clone;</li>
<li>get my feet wet with ncurses;</li>
<li>have some fun.</li>
</ul>
<p>and I guess I've achieved them all. even if it was not a big deal, it was my
first time with many things: a multiple files program (in C), a Makefile,
ncurses and small &quot;tricks&quot; I used in the code.</p>
<p>so it was worth it!</p>
<p>thank you for reading up to here, if you have any comment / suggestion or if you
found a bug, please contact me via email. bye.</p>]]></description>
        </item>

        <item>
            <title>installing only gnu/linux (debian jessie) on a mid 2011 imac</title>
            <pubDate>Sat, 03 Dec 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <link>https://marcolucidi01.github.io/posts/installing-only-gnu-linux-debian-jessie-on-a-mid-2011-imac.html</link>
            <guid>https://marcolucidi01.github.io/posts/installing-only-gnu-linux-debian-jessie-on-a-mid-2011-imac.html</guid>
            <source url="https://marcolucidi01.github.io/rss.xml">Marco Lucidi</source>
            <description><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=TPbx6QH_p0s"><strong>boot process video</strong></a></p>
<p>the reasons why I have done this are various, but I think, the most significant
is that, after using a linux distro daily on my laptop, going back on osx at
home was painful and I felt like in a &quot;cage&quot;. this was not good for me, and in
fact, I preferred to use the laptop even at home and, I stopped to use that imac
for a while.</p>
<p>then I realize that a full linux installation on a mac can be done easily, so, I
did some research (<a href="https://unix.stackexchange.com/questions/320107/installing-only-linux-on-a-mac-and-in-case-go-back-to-macos">question unix stackExchange</a>, <a href="https://wiki.archlinux.org/index.php/IMac_Aluminum">arch wiki</a>, <a href="https://wiki.debian.org/iMacIntel">debian
wiki</a>) and on a sunday morning I did it!</p>
<p>I have this little guy here (<a href="https://support.apple.com/kb/sp623?locale=en_US">imac12,1</a>), but with 8gb of ram which I
personally installed.</p>
<p>first of all, I made a <a href="https://support.apple.com/en-us/HT201372">macos installation media</a>, so, if in future I want, I
can reinstall it easily, since my intention was to completely format the hard
disk.</p>
<p>then I used a debian 8 <a href="https://www.debian.org/CD/netinst/">netinstall</a> through an usb drive, simply rebooted
holding down &quot;opt key&quot; and selected the right option. the installation was
completed without issues using the ethernet cable (the wifi has been also
recognized by the installer).</p>
<p>I installed kde and at the first reboot I got only the shell! unfortunately
<a href="https://packages.debian.org/stable/firmware-linux-nonfree">firmware-linux-nonfree</a> are required to get the radeon work!</p>
<h2>what did work out of the box</h2>
<ul>
<li><strong>ethernet</strong>: since the installer;</li>
<li><strong>wifi</strong>: I guess since the installer because it was recognized, but I can't
say for sure;</li>
<li><strong>usb</strong>: nothing to say;</li>
<li><strong>thunderbolt</strong>: tested with a second 1080p vga monitor that I use regularly
(the only thing I can test);</li>
<li><strong>speakers</strong>;</li>
<li><strong>camera and microphone</strong>: tested with vlc;</li>
<li><strong>suspend to ram</strong>: all good;</li>
<li><strong>cd/dvd</strong>: tested with k3b;</li>
</ul>
<h2>what did NOT work out of the box</h2>
<ul>
<li>
<p><strong>video card</strong>: as I said, firmware-linux-nonfree are required;</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>jack audio</strong>: small issue, fix:</p>
<pre><code># echo &quot;options snd-hda-intel model=imac27_122&quot; &gt;&gt; /etc/modprobe.d/imac\_local.conf
</code></pre>
<p>reboot. <a href="https://bugs.debian.org/cgi-bin/bugreport.cgi?bug=743936">Bugreport</a>;</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>apple wireless keyboard and magic mouse</strong>: fun fact, in the installer, I
did the entire process with the apple wireless keyboard, but then, once
debian was up and running, it didn't work anymore. I guess, bluetooth
drivers are missing, but I won't install them since I hate that things;</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>brightness</strong>: found a fix with xrandr:</p>
<pre><code>xrandr --output eDP --brightness 0.5
</code></pre>
</li>
</ul>
<p>I can't test the <strong>firewire port</strong> nor the <strong>sd reader</strong>.</p>
<p>finally I started to use this machine again!</p>]]></description>
        </item>

        <item>
            <title>encrypt a pen drive with LUKS on linux</title>
            <pubDate>Mon, 31 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <link>https://marcolucidi01.github.io/posts/encrypt-a-pen-drive-with-LUKS-on-linux.html</link>
            <guid>https://marcolucidi01.github.io/posts/encrypt-a-pen-drive-with-LUKS-on-linux.html</guid>
            <source url="https://marcolucidi01.github.io/rss.xml">Marco Lucidi</source>
            <description><![CDATA[<h2>info</h2>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://gitlab.com/cryptsetup/cryptsetup">cryptsetup</a> (repo) <a href="https://linux.die.net/man/8/cryptsetup">man</a> (man page)</li>
<li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Linux_Unified_Key_Setup">LUKS</a> (wikipedia)</li>
<li><a href="https://wiki.archlinux.org/index.php/Dm-crypt/Device_encryption">dm-crypt/Device encryption</a> (archwiki)</li>
</ul>
<h2>set up the drive</h2>
<p>first of all, we need to install <code>cryptsetup</code> on our system. I'm on debian so:</p>
<pre><code># apt-get install cryptsetup
</code></pre>
<p>after connecting the drive, we need to get the device name assigned to it:</p>
<pre><code># fdisk -l
</code></pre>
<p><img src="../imgs/fdisk-l.png" alt="fdisk-l" /></p>
<p>as you can see, in my case is <code>/dev/sdb</code>.</p>
<p>now, this step will destroy all data on the drive, MAKE SURE YOU HAVE A BACKUP
BEFORE PROCEEDING.</p>
<p><code>umount</code> your drive and then type:</p>
<pre><code># cryptsetup -y -v luksFormat your-device

-y: query for passwords twice
-v: verbose
</code></pre>
<p>and follow the instruction on screen.</p>
<p><img src="../imgs/cryptsetup-luksFormat.png" alt="cryptsetup-luksFormat" /></p>
<p>of course, several other options can be added, I'm ok with the defaults, but if
you want, in the info links, you will find suggestions to add other options.</p>
<p>ok, the device is encrypted. what's missing? a file system!</p>
<pre><code># cryptsetup luksOpen your-device name-you-want
</code></pre>
<p>to unlock the drive, you will be asked for the password of course</p>
<pre><code># mkfs -t ext4 /dev/mapper/name-you-used-before
</code></pre>
<p>and you will get a result similar to this:</p>
<p><img src="../imgs/mkfs-t-ext4.png" alt="mkfs-t-ext4" /></p>
<p>now we can actually mount the drive. here a picture, I'll explain in the next
section.</p>
<p><img src="../imgs/mount-luks.png" alt="mount-luks" /></p>
<h2>mount an encrypted drive</h2>
<p>many desktop environments (at least KDE) are capable to recognize a <code>LUKS</code> drive
when it is connected and do the dirty work for you</p>
<p><img src="../imgs/kde-mount-luks.png" alt="kde-mount-luks" /></p>
<p>but, since I'm a fan of command line (mainly because is a &quot;universal&quot; interface
among distributions), I'm going to show that way.</p>
<p>zero step: connect the drive and check the device name</p>
<p>first step: unlock the drive</p>
<pre><code># cryptsetup luksOpen your-device name-you-want
</code></pre>
<p>second step: mount the drive on a mount point</p>
<pre><code># mount /dev/mapper/name-you-used-before mount-point-you-like
</code></pre>
<p>(with file systems different from <code>ext</code> could be required to specify the type)</p>
<p>done!</p>
<p><img src="../imgs/luks-summary.png" alt="luks-summary" /></p>
<h2>umount an encrypted drive</h2>
<p>things are easy here:</p>
<pre><code># umount mount-point-used-before
# cryptsetup luksClose name-used-before
</code></pre>
<p>done!</p>
<h2>conclusion</h2>
<p>this isn't a professional tutorial, no argument has been deepened, it's just a
quick way to set up an encrypted pen drive (or external hard disk, sd card,
etc...) with a password that works well on linux.</p>
<p>I encourage you to explore more these topics starting from the links provided at
the beginning of the post to get a better understanding of what we did today.</p>]]></description>
        </item>

        <item>
            <title>virtualbox guest additions on debian</title>
            <pubDate>Mon, 08 Feb 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <link>https://marcolucidi01.github.io/posts/virtualbox-guest-additions-on-debian.html</link>
            <guid>https://marcolucidi01.github.io/posts/virtualbox-guest-additions-on-debian.html</guid>
            <source url="https://marcolucidi01.github.io/rss.xml">Marco Lucidi</source>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>ok, this is a post for myself: every time that I need to install a new vm on
<a href="https://www.virtualbox.org/">virtualbox</a> I systematically forget the steps to install guest additions!</p>
<p>most of the times, I install <a href="https://www.debian.org/">debian</a>, so this &quot;tutorial&quot; will be focused on this
particular linux distribution.</p>
<p>open a terminal:</p>
<pre><code># apt-get update &amp;&amp; apt-get upgrade
# apt-get install dkms
</code></pre>
<p>now from the <strong>Devices</strong> menu, click on &quot;Insert Guest Additions CD image...&quot;</p>
<p>if the .iso will not mount automatically, in a terminal:</p>
<pre><code># mount /media/cdrom
</code></pre>
<p>then:</p>
<pre><code># sh /media/cdrom/VBoxLinuxAdditions.run
# reboot
</code></pre>
<p>info: <a href="https://packages.debian.org/en/stable/dkms"><code>dkms</code></a></p>
<p>from virtualbox site: &quot;Be sure to install DKMS before installing the Linux
Guest Additions. If DKMS is not available or not installed, the guest kernel
modules will need to be recreated manually whenever the guest kernel is
updated&quot;.</p>
<p>actually these three packages are what we need for the guest additions:
<a href="https://packages.debian.org/en/stable/make"><code>make</code></a>, <a href="https://packages.debian.org/en/stable/gcc"><code>gcc</code></a>, <a href="https://packages.debian.org/en/stable/linux-headers-amd64"><code>linux-headers</code></a>, but they are included in
dependencies of <code>dkms</code> so they are installed automatically with <code>dkms</code>.</p>
<p>p.s. it's recommended to install <code>dkms</code> even on the host system.</p>
<p>if the installation failed, make sure that you have the last .iso available and
also the <a href="http://download.virtualbox.org/virtualbox/">last version of Virtualbox</a></p>]]></description>
        </item>

        <item>
            <title>how to share wifi connection over ethernet on linux</title>
            <pubDate>Thu, 03 Dec 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            <link>https://marcolucidi01.github.io/posts/how-to-share-wifi-connection-over-ethernet-on-linux.html</link>
            <guid>https://marcolucidi01.github.io/posts/how-to-share-wifi-connection-over-ethernet-on-linux.html</guid>
            <source url="https://marcolucidi01.github.io/rss.xml">Marco Lucidi</source>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>after watching the <strong><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=YIRWwKraoRk">video</a></strong>, maybe you want to know what exactly the
command does! well, I'll try to explain.</p>
<p>I write again the command here:</p>
<pre><code># iptables -t nat -A POSTROUTING -o wlan0 -s 192.168.2.108 -j MASQUERADE
</code></pre>
<p>of course this is an <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Iptables">iptables</a> rule which use the <a href="https://netfilter.org/documentation/HOWTO/NAT-HOWTO.html"><code>nat</code></a> table</p>
<pre><code>iptables -t nat
</code></pre>
<p>with this in effect, we tell iptables to manipulate the table (-t) <a href="https://netfilter.org/documentation/HOWTO/NAT-HOWTO.html"><code>nat</code></a></p>
<pre><code>-A POSTROUTING
</code></pre>
<p>append (<code>-A</code>) to chain <code>POSTROUTING</code>, the following rule</p>
<pre><code>-o wlan0
</code></pre>
<p>means that <code>wlan0</code> must be the outgoing interface of the packets</p>
<pre><code>-s 192.168.2.108 -j MASQUERADE
</code></pre>
<p>all packets which have as source address (<code>-s</code>) <code>192.168.2.108</code> (Xbox 360 IP)
will be <a href="http://www.tldp.org/HOWTO/IP-Masquerade-HOWTO/ipmasq-background2.1.html">masked</a> (<code>-j MASQUERADE</code>) and will come out through <code>wlan0</code> (<code>-o wlan0</code>).</p>
<p>for a better understanding what words like: <code>table</code>, <code>chain</code> etc.. mean, I
suggest you to read the <a href="https://netfilter.org/documentation/">iptables documentation</a>.</p>
<p>I hope I have helped you to share your wifi connection over ethernet!</p>]]></description>
        </item>

    </channel>
</rss>
